When was the first time you became aware
of and had a problem with I guess we'll
call
them enhanced interrogation techniques.
I had an inkling when I was still in
Pakistan. Uh we we captured so many
al-Qaeda fighters on the night of the
Abu Zvea capture that we had to bring
them into our safe house for
interrogation in shifts in a patty
wagon. And the first group of 10 came
out of the patty wagon and they were all
wearing hoods. And I said to one of the
one of my colleagues, he was working for
me. I said, 'Wh why are they hooded? And
he said, "We don't want them to see our
faces." And I I got angry and I said,
"Are you seriously telling me that you
have never read the Geneva Convention?
It is a war crime to put hoods on them.
Take the hoods off." And he said, "Stop.
don't take the hoods off. And I said,
I'm gonna report you to to headquarters.
And he said, I'm gonna report you to
headquarters. I said, fine. And I took
the hoods off. And we reported each
other to headquarters. And I was
reprimanded. So I thought, "Wow, well,
the Geneva Convention is crystal clear
that hooding a prisoner is a war crime.
I guess it's a new world. I'm going to
have to get used to it." But then I got
back from Pakistan in May of 2002 and I
was standing in the in the sandwich line
at the CIA cafeteria and a senior
officer walked up to me very casually
and he said, "Hey, I'm glad I ran into
you. Would you be interested in being
trained in the use of enhanced
interrogation techniques?" I had never
heard that term before. And I said,
"Enhanced interrogation techniques?
What's that mean?" And he said very
seriously, he said, 'We going to start
getting rough with these guys. And I
said, 'Well, what does that mean? And he
described these 10 techniques. And I
said, 'Th that sounds like a torture
program. And he said, no, it's not
torture. The Justice Department approved
it and the president signed off on it. I
said, uh, give me an hour. I I need an
hour to think about it. So I I just
walked out of the cafeteria. I went up
to the seventh floor of the CIA, which
was the executive floor. There was an
extraordinarily senior officer up there
for whom I had worked in the Middle East
10 years earlier. And I knocked on his
door and I said, I said, 'Hey, I need
some advice. Uh, I was just asked if I
want to be trained in these enhanced
interrogation techniques. What do you
think of that? And he said, first of
all, let's call a spade a spade. He
said, this is a torture program, and
torture is a slippery slope, and you
know how these guys are. Somebody's
going to go overboard, and they're going
to kill a prisoner. And when that
happens, there's going to be a
congressional investigation and there's
going to be a Justice Department
investigation and somebody's going to go
to prison. Do you want to go to prison?
And I said, "No, I don't want to go to
prison." So, I went back downstairs and
I said, "Look, I have an ethical and
moral problem with this and I think it's
illegal. I'm not interested." And I'm
sorry to tell you that of the 14 people
that were approached, I was the only one
who said no. And so I I had a friend in
the counterterrorism center who he
happens to be a psychiatrist and a
brigadier general and we go to the same
church. We're in the same men's group
and he came up to me uh a few days later
and he said, "You know they're calling
you the human rights guy behind your
back." I said, "Yeah, I know. I've heard
it." And he said, "You know that's not a
compliment, right?" And I said, "Steve,
I don't care. I'm on the right side of
this and they are not and I'm sticking
with my guns. What were some of the 10
on the list? Well, it started off with a
few that were very mild. I I would not
consider to be uh torture where, you
know, you grab somebody by the lapels
and give them a shake and say, "Answer
my questions, dog on you." Um, and then
it graduated to a smack on the belly. It
was called an attention slap cuz it
leaves a handprint. It makes a loud
cracking sound. Then it was a slap in
the face, but but it graduated to things
like um water boarding where the
prisoner is strapped down uh on a board.
His feet are elevated compared to his
his head. U cloth is put in his mouth
and then water is poured on his face and
it's supposed to induce a feeling of of
drowning. In fact, in the case of Abu
Zabeda, he did drown and had to be
revived uh because too much water had
gotten down his throat and his heart
stopped beating. But then there were a
couple of other things that I believed
were worse than uh water boarding. One
was called the cold cell where a
prisoner was stripped naked. He was
chained to an eyebolt in the ceiling
like this. His cell was chilled to 50°
F. And then every hour a CIA officer
would go into the cell and throw a
bucket of ice water on him. And we we
murdered several prisoners that way. Uh
they they died of hypothermia. There was
another one um that sounds like it's no
big deal, but it was sleep
deprivation. So again, you're stripped
naked, chained to that eyebolt in the
ceiling, so you can't kneel or lay or
get comfortable in any way. um loud acid
rock music is is uh is uh pumped into
the cell. These industrial strength
lights are on 24 hours a day. Well, we
know that this is according to the
American Psychological Association, the
APA, that people begin to lose their
minds around day seven with no sleep.
They begin to die around day nine, die
of organ failure. But the CIA was
authorized to keep people awake for up
to 12 days and people died because of
that uh that technique as well. So I
said, "Listen, you know, this this is so
clearly illegal." I had done some
research on my own. We we have a law in
this country called the Federal Torture
Act of 1946, which specifically outlawed
exactly those techniques that the CIA
was now using. And in fact, we executed
Japanese soldiers who had waterboarded
American PS during the Second World War.
Furthermore, in January of 1968, the
Washington Post ran a front page
photograph of an American soldier
waterboarding a North Vietnamese
prisoner. On the day that that picture
was published, Secretary of Defense
Robert McNamera ordered an
investigation. The soldier was arrested.
He was convicted of torture and
sentenced to 20 years at Levvenworth and
then like magic in 2002 all these things
are suddenly legal. Well, we never we
never amended the law. The law never
changed. We changed. We took on this
this air of victimhood that because we
were the good guys and we lost 3,000
civilians on September 11th that it was
okay for us to do this because we had to
stop this existential threat that
al-Qaeda had become. Let's cut to the
chase. Your savings could be in serious
trouble. When Elon Musk is out here
warning us to brace for temporary
hardship, you might want to listen. I
trust Preserve Gold to safeguard my
accounts and I urge you to do the same.
They're the only precious metals company
I recommend. Are you going to sit back
and hope for the best or take control of
your financial future? Text Dr. Phil to
5050 to get your free precious metals
guide from Preserve Gold. With gold
prices recently breaking records and
analysts predicting this trend to
continue through 2025, you cannot afford
to wait. As a bonus, you can get up to
$15,000 with a qualified purchase from
Preserve Gold. So don't wait. Text Dr.
Phil to
5050. That's Dr.
Phill55 today. Once you became aware of
all this going on, how did you become a
whistleblower? How did you actually do
it? Only very reluctantly. And I'll tell
you, I wish that I could tell you that I
stood up and I told them, you know,
that's not the way it happened at all.
This was clearly illegal in my view. So
I waited for somebody who was directly
involved in the torture uh to come
forward and go public. I actually got
promoted on the strength of the Abu
Zubeta capture and I I was promoted to
become the uh executive assistant to the
CIA's deputy director for operations. So
in that position, it's such a stressful
position that you can only do it for a
year. You know, you're in the office at
3:45 a.m. You're briefing the deputy
director at 6:00. You brief the director
at 7. So, it's it's tough. Uh, but it
also gave me access to literally
everything that the CIA was doing around
the world for that one year. And so, I'm
following this enhanced interrogation
situation at a secret prison overseas.
And um, I kept waiting for somebody to
to come uh forward and and blow the
whistle on it because people were
writing in classified channels, hey, I'm
a I'm a medical doctor. I took a
hypocratic oath. this is not what I
signed up for. I'm not doing this. I
quit. I want to come back to
headquarters. So, there were, you know,
dozens of people objecting to this
program. I thought certainly somebody's
going to say something and nobody did.
Finally, I resigned
um to go into the the private sector. I
wasn't making enough money to put five
kids through college. So, I had to I had
to do something different.
And two and a half years after I
resigned, I got a call from Brian Ross
at ABC News. I had never spoken to a
journalist before. So I didn't know
about these journalist tricks. But he
said that he had a source who said that
I had uh I had tortured Abu Zuba. I said
absolutely untrue. I was the only person
who was kind to Abu Zubeda. I said I
never laid a hand on Abu Zubeda or on
any other prisoner. your your source is
either grossly misinformed or he's a
liar. And like I said, I didn't know
these reporters tricks. And Brian Ross
said, "Well, you're welcome to come on
the show and defend yourself." I said,
"Uh, yeah, I'll think about it." A
couple of days later, President George
W. Bush is giving a press conference.
And he looked right in the camera and he
said, "We do not torture like that." And
I said to my wife, who was also a senior
CIA officer, I said, "He is looking the
American people in the eye and he's
lying to them." And then two days later,
it was a Friday and the president had
walked out of the South Portico of the
White House. He was walking to the
helicopter to go to uh Camp David and a
reporter shouted a question about
torture. And the president stopped and
turned and said, "Well, if there is
torture, it's becau it's because of a
rogue CIA officer." And I told my wife,
"Brian Ross's source is at the White
House and they're going to try to pin
this on me." So I called Brian Ross and
I said, "I'll do your show." And I
decided in the four or five days, you
know, between that call and the show
that no matter what he asked me, I was
going to tell the truth and let the
cards fall where they may. And that's
how it happened. So you went on ABC News
interview. You said what you said about
what was going on and clearly stated you
didn't involve yourself in torture. You
were recruited. You were asked to do it,
declined.
Correct. But you didn't deny that it was
going on. Correct. I said three things
that that
that caused the controversy. I said that
the CIA was torturing its prisoners. I
said that prisoners were
um that um I'm sorry, CIA was torturing
its prisoners. That that torture was
official US government policy. There was
no rogue CIA officer. and I said that
the policy had been personally approved
by the president. And here's where it
gets
weird. A, as you might expect, the the
CIA uh filed what's called a crimes
report against me with the FBI, saying
that I had revealed classified
information to the public. So, the FBI
investigated me from December of 2007 to
December of 2008. And then in December
of 2008, they they sent my attorneys a
declination letter declining to
prosecute me. They said
that Human Rights Watch, Amnesty
International, and the International
Committee of the Red Cross, Red Cross
had all published papers saying that the
CIA was torturing its prisoners, that it
was the worst kept secret in Washington.
So, they declined to prosecute. My wife
and I actually went out to dinner that
night to celebrate.
And then three weeks later, Barack Obama
becomes president and he names John
Brennan as the deputy national security
adviser for counterterrorism. John and I
always disliked each other. I never
trusted him. I never liked him. And he
was one of the godfathers of the torture
program. All of a sudden, he's
pretending to be whatever he is, a
Democrat. I don't know.
I had no idea that within days of
Obama's inauguration, John Brennan asked
the Justice Department to secretly
reopen the case against me. And so for
the next three years, my phones were
tapped, my emails were intercepted, and
teams of FBI agents um followed me
everywhere I went, even into church. We
learn later we we received 15,000 pages
of discovery after I was charged. I was
charged in January of of 2012 with five
felonies including three counts of
espionage. And remember espionage can be
a death penalty charge and I had three
counts. So, we we learned in
Discovery that Brennan had written a
memo to Eric Holder, the attorney
general, and he said, "Charge him with
espionage." And Eric Holder wrote back
and said, "My people don't think he
committed espionage." And then Brennan
wrote back and said, "Charge him anyway
and make him defend himself." And so
they did. And then 10 months later, I
went bankrupt under the weight of $1.15
million in legal fees. And as soon as I
went bankrupt, they dropped the
espionage charges.